Finding Aid for Henry Wade Rogers papers, 1873-1920
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Henry Wade Rogers papers 1873-1920
Rogers, Henry Wade, 1853-1926.
1 linear ft.
852211 Aa 2
Professor of law at the University of Michigan and Northwestern University. Papers consist of a scrapbook containing programs and invitations largely connected with Northwestern University, miscellaneous letters received while professor at University of Michigan, many relating to speaking engagements; and manuscript biography of Thomas M. Cooley.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donor No. 385.
The collection is open to research.
Henry Wade Rogers was born in 1853 in Holland Patent, near Utica, New York. He graduated from the University of Michigan in 1874, and from the law school in 1877. He practiced law in Minneapolis, and then New Jersey, until 1882, when he returned to the University of Michigan to become Taping professor of law. In 1885, he became professor of Roman law, and in the following year, he succeeded Thomas M. Cooley to become dean of the Department of Law. He was also lecturer on domestic relations and criminal law in 1890-1891.
In 1890 he left the university to become president of Northwestern University, where he remained for ten years. He was chairman of the World's Congress on Jurisprudence and Law Reform at the Chicago Exposition of 1893, and general chairman of the Saratoga Conference on the Foreign Policy of the United States in 1898.
Rogers resigned from his position at Northwestern to join the Yale Law School, first as a lecturer, then as professor of law and finally as dean of the school from 1903 to 1916. He also served as president of the Association of American Law Schools in 1906, and as chairman of the American Bar Association's Committee on Legal Education and Admission to the Bar from 1905 to 1917. In 1913, President Woodrow Wilson appointed him federal judge to the Second Judicial Circuit Court of Appeals.
Rogers held the chair of jurisprudence at Yale until his retirement in 192 1. He died in 1926 at the age of seventy-two.
The Henry Wade Rogers papers consist of a scrapbook containing programs and invitations largely connected with Northwestern University, miscellaneous letters received while professor at University of Michigan, many relating to speaking engagements; and a manuscript biography of Thomas M. Cooley. The papers are organized in to three series: Correspondence, 1873-1920; Thomas M. Cooley; and Scrapbook. Correspondents include: Thomas F. Bayard, George Biddle, Henry B. Brown, Grover Cleveland, Thomas M. Cooley, Henry S. Frieze, Melville W. Fuller, Joseph E. Gary, John M. Harlan, James McMillan, Samuel Maxwell, Samuel F. Miller, John P. Newman, George P.
Subjects:
Cooley, Thomas McIntyre, 1824-1898.; Cooley family.; Judges--Michigan.; Lawyers--Michigan.; Northwestern University (Evanston, Ill.); Rogers, Henry Wade, 1853-1926.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Law.
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Bayard, Thomas F. (Thomas Francis), 1828-1898.; Biddle, George.; Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908.; Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.; Frieze, Henry S. (Henry Simmons), 1817-1889.; Fuller, Melville Weston, 1833-1910.; Gary, J. E. (Joseph Easton), 1821-1906.; Harlan, John Marshall, 1833-1911.; Hoar, George Frisbie, 1826-1904.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Kent, Charles A. (Charles Artemis), 1835-1917.; McMillan, James, 1838-1902.; Maxwell, Samuel, 1826-1901.; Miller, Samuel Freeman, 1816-1890.; Newman, John Philip, 1826-1899.; Putnam, George Palmer, 1887-1950.; Vincent, John Heyl, 1832-1920.; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.
Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  - 1873-1888 and undated (Box 1)
  - 1889 (Box 1)
  - 1890 and 1898 (Box 1)
  - January-July 1901 (Box 1)
  - August-September 1901 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1901 (Box 1)
  - 1902 (Box 1)
  - 1914-1920 and undated (Box 1)
- Thomas M. Cooley
  - Manuscript of Thomas Cooley's lecture, "The Place of the Federal Supreme Court in the Constitutional System of the United States." (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of Cooley biography; chapters entitled:
    - Ancestry and boyhood (Box 1)
    - Early years in Michigan (Box 1)
    - Characteristics (Box 1)
    - Authorship (Box 1)
    - Addresses (Box 1)
    - Political relations (Box 1)
    - Chairman of Interstate Commerce Commission (Box 1)
    - Religion (Box 1)
    - Railroad arbitrator and receiver (Box 1)
    - President of the American Bar Association (Box 1)
    - Washington life (Box 1)
    - The Last Years (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 1)
- Scrapbook
  - 1894-1897 (Box 1)
    (including programs, invitations, etc., largely of Northwestern University, but also The University of Michigan, and the University of Chicago)
Partial Index to Correspondence
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.
August 18, 1901
Bayard, Thomas Francis, 1828-1898.
1889
Biddle, George
1889
Cleveland, Grover, Pres. U.S., 1837-1908.
April 2, 1890
Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.
July 29, September 17, October 13, 1901
Frieze, Henry Simmons, 1817-1889.
1887
Fuller, Melville Weston, 1833-1910.
1888, 1890
Gary, Joseph Easton, 1821-1903.
1888
Harlan, John Marshall, 1833-1911.
April 25, 1889.
Hoar, George Frisbie, 1826-1904
November 12, 1901
Hutchins, Harry Burns, 1847-1930.
October 10, 1901
Kent, Charles Artemas, 1835-1917.
September 27, 1901.
McMillan, James, 1838-1902.
1889
Maxwell, Samuel, 1826-1901.
1889
Miller, Samuel Freeman, 1816-1890.
1880, 1886
Newman, John Philip, 1826-1899.
1889-1890
Vincent, John Heyl, 1832-1920.
1888-1889
Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.
1889, 1890